Eric Malcolm

Front-End Developer, Architect, UX & Accessibility

313.434.5048 | eric@malcolmdigital.com | ericmalcolm.com | linkedin.com/in/ericmalcolm

Summary & Skills

I help architect and develop solutions to create usable, human-friendly and accessible websites, interfaces, and apps. After discovering my passion for web design I naturally progressed to web development. With 10+years' experience in web development, I have become well-versed in many areas of the web including:

Front-End Development:

- HTML5 / CSS3 / SCSS / JS / ES6 / JSON
- React / Redux / TypeScript / PropTypes
- Storybook / Jest / React Testing Library
- React Native / Expo
- Browser Developer Tools / Inspector / Console / Network
- Bootstrap / Foundation / HTML Emails
- Test Driven Development / Pair
 Programming / Mob Programming
- Code Management / Version Control (Git)
- Design, Architecture & Code Reviews

Software Development Life Cycle:

- Agile/Scrum Methodology
- Acceptance Testing & Validation
- Environment Management & Deployment
- Continuous Integration & Deployment with TeamCity & Jenkins

Leadership & Workflow:

- Establish Development Processes & Technical Documentation
- Feature, User Story, and Task Estimation
- Project & Platform Management
- Team Management & Delegation

Accessibility (a11y):

- WCAG 2.0 & 2.1, ARIA, Section 508, ADA Compliance
- Creating an Accessible User Experience
- axe DevTools, axe Auditor, and axe Monitor

User-Centered Design & Development:

- Usability / UI / UX Focused
- Mobile First / Responsive Design

Information Architecture:

- Content Structure & Strategy
- Search Engine Optimization

Adobe Experience Manager (AEM):

- 5.6, 6.0 (Adobe Trained), 6.1 to 6.5
- Sightly Component Development, Touch-Optimized UI, Templates, Workflows, API Implementations
- React within AEM / SPA Editor
- AEM Environment Architecture and Configuration
- Working with OSGi, CRX, JCR
- Authoring, Publishing, Activation, and Replication

WordPress / WooCommerce Design & Development:

- Custom WordPress Installation
- Theme & Plugin Development
- WordPress Style PHP
- React on top of WP REST API
- Website Maintenance & Management
- Ecommerce Setup & Management
- WordPress Multi-User & Scaling WordPress

Experience

Director of Technology

VMLY&R

May 2022 - Present

Detroit, MI (Remote)

Sherwin Williams - Color Journey

May 2022 - Present

Helped successfully launch a new color journey experience for Sherwin Williams customers as the lead developer on an AEM 6.5 platform with React.

Responsibilities:

- Leading the development team of junior, mid-level, and senior developers
- AEM Component Development
- Front-End Architecture Guidance
- React Component Development
- Storybook Implementation
- Accessibility Compliance Review and Development WCAG 2.0 AA
- Mentoring and training developers
 - o React / State Management
 - AEM Architecture and Setup

Business/Technology Value:

- Helped lead the successful launch of a new Color Journey experience in a newer AEM setup that the company has begun transitioning to.
 - Color Detail Pages
 - Color Detail Hero Single Page Application for easier transitions of colors
 - o Scene Visualizer
 - Color Grids
 - Color Swatches

Senior Technical Consultant

Perficient

October 2019 - May 2022

Livonia, MI (Remote)

Ford Ecommerce

May 2020 - April 2022

Participated, trained and guided an agile team to successfully launch part of an AEM 6.4 ecommerce application across multiple markets in North America and Europe.

Responsibilities:

- Front-End Architecture Guidance
- React Component Development
- Redux, Thunks, Actions, Reducers, Selectors Implementation and Planning
- Storybook Implementation
- Testing / Test Driven Development
- AEM Architecture Planning
- AEM Component Development
- AEM SPA Editor with React
- Accessibility Compliance Review and Development WCAG 2.0 AA
- Lead the team at multiple times when we had no official Anchor / Lead Developer
- Trained many developers and Anchors on the project: 5 Anchors, 10+ Developers
 - React / Redux
 - AEM Architecture and Setup
 - API Architecture

Business/Technology Value:

- Helped manage the successful launch of the Mustang Mach-E Reservation Flow for North America.
- Helped lead the successful launch of an Ecommerce Cart in North America and Europe for the Mustang Mach-E & Other Eligible Vehicles
 - Payment Calculator, Trade In, Accessories, Charging, Delivery

Ford Credit

January 2020 - May 2020

Helped guide an agile team to successfully launch an AEM 6.4 website platform with multiple financial services marketing websites.

Responsibilities:

- Process Implementation and Documentation Helping to Organize an Agile Team
- AEM Architecture Planning
- AEM Component Development
- Helped Establish an Internal Design System for the Branding and Re-utilizing of Elements
- Accessibility Compliance Review and Development WCAG 2.0 AA

Business/Technology Value:

 Helped manage the successful launch of an AEM 6.4 website platform by following Adobe guidelines/standards: architecture, templates, extending out of the box components, etc. This allows the business to author components much easier and the development team to upgrade easier and re-utilize components.

Michigan Hispanic Collaborative

October 2019 - January 2020

Worked with a small team to extend a website into a non-profit website platform for helping minorities obtain resources to achieve a higher education. Oversaw the development and implementation of core features on a WordPress based platform with the LearnDash Learning Management System (LMS).

Responsibilities:

- Worked on the Implementation of Core Features for the Platform: User Management, Content Restriction, Custom Post Types, LMS
- Helped the team work on some enhancements to launch the product.

Business/Technology Value:

• Gathered the initial requirements from the non-profit and turned them into actionable functionality within the platform to develop a minimum viable product.

Front-End Accessibility Developer

Regions Bank

June 2018 - Present

Birmingham, AL (Remote)

Digital Banking Platforms

Led accessibility compliance efforts across multiple agile teams supporting large scale digital banking projects.

Responsibilities:

- Reviewing Websites and Web Apps to Meet WCAG 2.0 AA, Section 508 & ADA Compliance
- Coding, Testing & Debugging the Front-End of Websites & Web Apps
- Advocating for accessibility across digital banking properties.
- Teaching and guiding agile teams to incorporate accessibility from the beginning and build accessible components and products.
- Building Responsive Accessible Components with an Internal Design System

Business/Technology Value:

- Getting the various websites and properties up to snuff with web accessibility and ADA standards to give customers the best online digital experience.
- By reviewing websites and apps for accessibility, we ensure an equal customer experience as well as prevent potential legal action.
- Creating a unified customer experience across the bank makes it easier for customers to use our products and services, increases retention, and minimizes unnecessary call center support interactions.

Technical Lead; Owner

Malcolm Digital

September 2010 - Present

Sterling Heights, MI

As a freelance web designer, developer and strategist I build client websites and help them grow their business. Started in 2010 to provide services for select projects, focusing on Optimized Websites and Content Driven Marketing.

Responsibilities:

Maintaining Multiple Ongoing Projects and Client Relationships

- Planning Responsive Website Design, Usability, and User Experience
- Design / Development / Maintenance Client Websites WordPress, WooCommerce, Static and Apps
- Optimizing Website Content and Performance for SEO Analytics & Conversion Tracking
- Coding, Testing & Debugging HTML5 / CSS3 / LESS / SASS / JS / AJAX / JSON / AngularJS / React / React Native / WordPress / PHP

Business/Technology Value:

- Gave businesses the platform to make money online through ecommerce applications.
- Allow businesses to maintain their own website through a maintained set of components.
- Helped increase revenue for small businesses through mobile websites, seo, ppc and social marketing.
- Performing ongoing site maintenance for customers, so they can focus on running their business.

Senior Web Developer - Team Lead

Optum Technology

Jan 2017 - June 2018

Southfield, MI

Responsible for the front-end development, AEM consulting/development and leading teams on internal/client projects: websites and applications for consumer, provider, and physician support. Responsibilities include:

- Leading an Agile Development Team Architecting and Creating Components in a Design System for an AEM Based Digital Marketing Platform
- Coding, Testing & Debugging HTML5 / CSS3 / LESS / JS / AJAX / JSON / AngularJS / AEM / React
- Building Accessible Websites and Web Apps to Meet WCAG 2.0, Section 508 & ADA Compliance
- Planning, Facilitating & Building Responsive Sightly Components with AEM 5.6, 6.0, 6.1, 6.2 & 6.3
- Creating Usable Websites / Web Apps on Multiple Devices, Browsers and Screen Sizes

Senior Web Developer

May 2014 - Jan 2017

Responsible for the front-end development, design system integration, and AEM consulting/development on internal/client projects: websites and applications for consumer, provider, and physician support. Responsibilities included:

- Coding, Testing & Debugging HTML5 / CSS3 / LESS / SASS / JS / AEM / AngularJS / React
- Building Accessible Websites and Web Apps to Meet WCAG 2.0, Section 508 & ADA Compliance
- Planning, Facilitating & Building Responsive Sightly Components with AEM 5.6, 6.0, 6.1 & 6.2
- Creating Usable Websites / Web Apps on Multiple Devices, Browsers and Screen Sizes

Webmaster, Web Designer & Media Strategist

Lifestyle Lift

Troy, MI

As the webmaster I managed, strategized, and implemented solutions an all web properties of Lifestyle Lift. Lifestyle Lift provided a specialized cosmetic facial procedure to patients in 70+ centers nationwide. Responsibilities included:

- Usability, User Experience and Marketing Planning for 75+ Responsive Web Properties
- Design, Development, Optimization and Content Management of Main Website, Local Websites, Landing Pages and Microsites

User Interface / Web Designer

Search Optics

January 2012 - November 2013

Ferndale, MI

As a part of the design team, I planned out and designed responsive automotive dealer websites. Search Optics is a digital marketing company that turns virtual traffic into measurable results. Responsibilities included:

- Basic User Experience Research and Design
- Responsive Website/User Interface Design / Landing Page Design
- Logo Design / Branding / Slide and Banner Design
- Email Marketing Design and Coding / Social Media Graphics / Flash Display Ad Design

Front-End Web Developer / Designer

Lifestyle Lift

January 2011 - January 2012

Troy, MI

As part of the Web Design and Online Marketing Team I planned out, designed and developed web properties for 60+ centers nationwide. Responsibilities included:

- Design & Development of Microsites, New Local Sites and Landing Pages
- Local Search Engine Optimization and Google Analytics Tracking
- Display Ad Design and Other Graphic Design
- Design, Development of Joomla-based Intranet

Freelance Graphic + Web Designer & **Developer**

Warren. MI

June 2008 - September 2010

As a freelance designer & developer getting my start I focused on basic business needs and building client websites. I started freelancing while in school for Graphic & Digital Media Design. Responsibilities included:

- Graphic Design: Brochures, Business Cards, etc.
- Print Page Layout and Editing
- Web Design Layouts & Graphics
- Web Development

Freelance

Programming Languages, Frameworks, Technologies, Guidelines, etc.

HTML5, CSS3, LESS, SASS, JS, jQuery, Sightly, AEM, WordPress, WooCommerce, Bootstrap, Foundation, HTML Emails, Git, WCAG, WAI-ARIA, Section 508 Compliance, ADA Compliance, Agile, Angular, React, React Native, Grunt, Gulp, Webpack, UI Design, UX Design, Responsive Web Design, Front-End Development, SEO, Usability, Accessibility, Cross-Browser Compatibility, and more.

Education

Bachelor's of Technology, Digital Media Design

Baker College of Clinton Township, 2009 - 2011

Associates of Business, Graphic Design

Baker College of Clinton Township, 2006 - 2009

Certifications

Adobe Experience Manager/AEM 6.0 Developer

Adobe, June 2015

Volunteering

WordCamp Detroit - Organizer

2020 - Present

Working with other co-organizers to coordinate a great Tech Conference focused on WordPress!

- 2020 June 13th at Wayne State University
- detroit.wordcamp.org

Metro Detroit WordPress Meetup - Lead Organizer

August 2013 - January 2020

Working with other co-leaders, I helped coordinate different speakers to talk about WordPress to users, designers and developers in Metro Detroit at monthly meetups.

twitter.com/metrodetroitwp

WordCamp Detroit - Lead Organizer

2017 - 2019

Leading the effort and working with other organizers to coordinate a great Tech Conference focused on WordPress!

- 2018 April 28th at Grand Circus Detroit
- 2019 May 18th at Cass Tech High School
- detroit.wordcamp.org

Boy Scouts of America - Treasurer

2016 - 2019

As the pack treasurer I ensure the pack's finances are sound, helping the committee and the Cubmaster establish a pack budget plan. Other responsibilities include collecting dues from den leaders, checking pack disbursements against budget allowances and paying bills.

Community Volunteer for Social Responsibility Team - Optum Technology

2015 - 2018

For a few years, along with the rest of the social responsibility team, we helped out in different aspects of community and social service. Some examples include: Book Drives, Glove Drives, Blanket Drives, Toys for Tots, Community Farming, Food Bank Volunteering and more.